Personal Info

Phone: +46 733 777 123

Email: jonas[REMOVE]@jonasboner.com Website: http://jonasboner.com/ Company: http://scalablesolutions.se/

Address: Näckrosgatan 3G, 75437 Uppsala, Sweden

Highlights

I am a pragmatic who is passionate about technology, learning new things and helping others to work better and more effectively. I am a programmer, mentor, speaker and author who spends most of my time consulting, hacking on open source as well as lecturing and speaking at developer conferences world-wide. I have worked at Terracotta, the JRockit JVM at BEA and am an active contributor to the Open Source community; most notably created the AspectWerkz Aspect-Oriented Programming (AOP) framework, committer to the Terracotta JVM clustering technology and been part of the Eclipse AspectJ team.

Specialities

Java, Scala, JEE, Design, Object-Oriented Programming, Aspect-Oriented Programming, Functional Programming, Agile Coaching and Mentoring, Open Source Strategy and Community Building, Domain-Driven Design, Test-Driven Development, Web and Enterprise Development, System Architecture, Distributed and Concurrent Computing, Bytecode Manipulation and Compiler Design.

Work Experience

• Founder and Consultant, Scalable Solutions, Sweden

2009 - present

- Consultant, mentor, speaker, teacher, agile coach. http://scalable solutions.se/

• Co-Founder and CTO, Triental AB, Sweden

2008 - 2009

- Team lead, agile coach, developer and architect.
- Building a finance product suite for private banking and wealth management using Scala and JEE. http://triental.com/

• Senior Software Engineer, Terracotta, Inc., US

2005 - 2008

- Team lead and agile coach.
- Worked on Terracottas core JVM-level clustering technology, including runtime bytecode manipulation, AOP technologies, high performant multi-threaded code, integration with various Open Source frameworks etc.
- Technical evangelist writing articles and speaking at conferences, Java User Groups etc.
- Strategic due diligence.
- Open Source strategy, community building and marketing.

http://www.terracotta.org/

• Senior Software Engineer, BEA Systems, Sweden

2003 - 2005

- Worked in the JRockit (JVM) Team on design, architecture and development in the fields of AOP, runtime tools, JVM support for AOP as well as technology evangelism (speaking at conferences, writing articles and papers etc).

http://bea.com/

• System Architect, Sony NetServices, Austria

2002 - 2003

- Worked as a system architect at Sony designing and developing system ranging from large-scale enterprise application systems to digital TV and mobile technologies.

http://www.sonynetservices.com/

• JEE Consultant, Consafe Infotech, Sweden

2000 - 2002

- Worked as a JEE consultant, implemented various enterprise application systems using state-of-the-art techniques and technologies.

http://www.consafeinfotech.se/

Selected Technical Skills

Scala, Java, Clojure, Ruby, Erlang, Python, Mozart/Oz, Haskell, Common Lisp, JavaScript, AJAX, Wicket, jQuery, SQL, UML, JEE, EJB, RMI, Servlets, JSP, JSF, JPA, JDO, SCA, WebServices, JMS, JDBC, HTML, XML, SAX, DOM, StAX, JAXB, AspectJ, AspectWerkz, Spring, Hibernate, Terracotta, RIFE, Struts, WLS, WebSphere, Jetty, Geronimo, Tomcat, JBoss, Win32, Unix, Linux, Mac etc.

Open Source

• Terracotta

- Committer to the Terracotta JVM-level clustering technology, other responsibilities included technical evangelism, strategy, community building, support, marketing, QA and project management. - Terracotta is Open Source JVM-level clustering for Java.

http://terracotta.org/

• AspectWerkz

- Founder, architect and lead developer of the AspectWerkz project, other responsibilities included support, marketing, QA and project management.
- AspectWerkz is a high-performant, dynamic, lightweight and powerful AOP framework/compiler/runtime for Java, which utilizes bytecode manipulation to instrument classes at build-time, class load time or runtime (JIT).

http://aspectwerkz.codehaus.org/

• AspectJ

- Member of the AspectJ Team at Eclipse.
- AspectJ is an AOP framework/compiler/runtime for Java (can be used either through a language extension to Java or through plain Java). It became the defacto standard for AOP in Java after merging with AspectWerkz in 2005.

http://www.eclipse.org/aspectj/

• backport175

- Founder and lead developer of the backport175 compiler.
- backport175 is a fully compliant backport of the Java 5 annotations (JSR-175) specification. Making strongly typed annotations available for JDK 1.3/1.4. They are bytecode compatible with Java 5 annotations making them available for use by standard tools (APT, IDEs etc.). http://backport175.codehaus.org/

• Scala OTP

- Founder and committer to the Scala OTP project.
- The Scala OTP project implements a platform and runtime for deployment, execution and management of Scala Actors, similar to Erlangs OTP platform, for implementation of highly fault-tolerant, distributed actor-based enterprise systems.

http://github.com/jboner/scala-otp/

Publications

Selected Industry Articles

- Distributed Web Continuations with RIFE and Terracotta, August 2007 http://www.artima.com/lejava/articles/distributed_continuationsP.html
- Web Applications with Spring Web Flow and Terracotta for Spring, April 2007 http://www.infoq.com/articles/spring-web-flow-terracotta
- How to Build a POJO-based Data Grid using Open Terracotta, January 2007 http://jonasboner.com/2007/01/29/how-to-build-a-pojo-based-data-grid-using-open-terracotta/
- Distributed Computing Made Easy, TheServerSide.com, May 2006. http://www.theserverside.com/tt/articles/article.tss?l=DistCompute
- JRockit JVM support for AOP Part 1, dev2dev.com, July 2005 http://dev2dev.bea.com/pub/a/2005/08/jvmaop1.html
- JRockit JVM support for AOP Part 2, dev2dev.com, July 2005 http://dev2dev.bea.com/pub/a/2005/08/jvmaop2.html
- AspectWerkz 2: An Extensible Aspect Container, TheServerSide.com, November 2004 http://www.theserverside.com/articles/article.tss?l=AspectWerkzP1

Academic Articles

Clustering the Java Virtual Machine using Aspect-Oriented Programming, March 2007
AOSD 2007

http://www.jonasboner.com/public/publications/AOSD2007Final.pdf

Java Virtual Machine support for Aspect-Oriented Programming, March 2006
AOSD 2006

http://www.jonasboner.com/public/publications/JVMAOPAOSD2006.pdf

• What are the key issues for commercial AOP use - and how does AspectWerkz address them?, March 2005

Invited Industry Talk for AOSD 2005

 $http://www.jonasboner.com/public/publications/aosd2004 invited talk_aspectwerkz.pdf$

• AspectWerkz: Dynamic AOP for Java, March 2004.

AOSD 2004

http://www.jonasboner.com/public/publications/aosd2004_aspectwerkz.pdf

A complete listing can be found at: http://jonasboner.com/articles/

Education

• Certified ScrumMaster Scrum Alliance (Ken Schwaber), 2006

- B.Sc. in Computer Science Mid Sweden University, 2000
- Various courses in Mathematics University of Stockholm, 1996

$Speaking\ Engagements$

A complete list can be found at: http://jonasboner.com/talks

Awards, Interviews etc.

• JetBrains Academy

Invited into the JetBrains Academy. http://www.jetbrains.com/devnet/whos/index.html

• Award: Who Is Who In Enterprise Java 2004?

Voted in as part of The Middleware Companys list of the 52 most influential leading experts in the Java enterprise community (world-wide).

- Interviewed by InfoQ on Terracotta for Spring, XA compliance, Data Grids etc., Sept 2006. http://www.infoq.com/news/terracotta-spring
- Interviewed by JayWay on AOP, distributed computing etc., April 2006. http://www.jayway.se/download/JayView10_2006.pdf

 \bullet Interviewed by Java Hispano on commercialization, current status and future of AOP etc., November 2004.

 $http://www.javahispano.org/text.viewer.action?file=jonas_en$

References

Available upon request. Some endorsements can be found on Linked In. http://www.linkedin.com/in/jonasboner